<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>rayanon</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2017-02-20T19:30:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Rubbish</title><link href="/writing-dopamine.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-20T19:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-02-20T19:30:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Anon Ray</name></author><id>tag:None,2017-02-20:/writing-dopamine.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello, I'm writing some notes here. I see a complete white screen infront of
me, which is supposed to give me a distraction-free writing experience. But I'm
not sure if this is entirely true that it happens. For example, when I looked
at the screen it kind of felt awkward …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello, I'm writing some notes here. I see a complete white screen infront of
me, which is supposed to give me a distraction-free writing experience. But I'm
not sure if this is entirely true that it happens. For example, when I looked
at the screen it kind of felt awkward that its completely white and now I have
to surrender myself to the serene feeling of white and transcend to a higher
level to get some inspiration for my writing. But I also see a point that when
someone has already some idea on what to write about, when they see the
complete white screen they can concentrate on their mind and the just the words
that flow out of their fingers into this screen which might obviously be a very
good writing experience, to the point it is almost a dopamine trip I suppose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: This was written to try out a new note taking app. After writing it out
thought of posting it here.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="random"></category><category term="dopamine"></category></entry><entry><title>The story of my first log</title><link href="/first-log.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-02-09T14:17:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-02-09T14:17:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Anon Ray</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-02-09:/first-log.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Boring story of why I started this blog&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a very boring story of why I started this blog. Please read it at your
own risk!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="To blog or not to blog" class="center-img" src="/images/to-blog-or-not-to-blog.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around 2004-2009 netizens (or citizens of the Internet) became quite obsessed
with something called blog. Blog is a truncation of the expression web log.
Which essentially means a log of yourself on the World Wide Web. Blogs became
hugely popular, where individuals published their own website with their own
personal opinions or biased/unbiased, correct/incorrect information. All was
well and blogs were thriving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But since 2009, individual website publishing saw a drop and more people
flocked to larger platforms for blogging, established by companies which
offered them ease of getting started to publish content; while sacrificing the
freedom and flexibility that came with individual website publishing.
Eventually, even larger companies got established, and they changed the way
people used to blog by offering proprietary ways of publishing content: like
via a tweet or via a post, which forces the user to write and format the
content according to their pre-defined template of a tweet/post. This was the
boom of social networks, and people could express how much they wanted with
photographs, selfies and their own day-to-day activities; which became less
artistic and more competitive (because people cared less of what and how they
are expressing, and more on the quantity of posts and likes and comments and
such). So a lot of people consider that was the death of blogging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But people in the world of software were already writing blogs since the birth
of the World Wide Web; and they kept maintaining their own blogs even after
bigger publishing platforms took over the majority of blogging population.
These people were mostly web developers, and other software engineers who knew
the basics of web publishing - that is running one's own website, hosting etc.
Even if they were not managing their own hosting, they probably had an
independent blog on managed infrastructure, and refrained from migrating
entirely to any MegaCorp Inc. publishing platforms.  So, in short, if you are
person in &lt;em&gt;tech&lt;/em&gt;, you probably run your own blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not me. Even after being in the world of software and working as a web
developer for quite sometime, I have never had a blog. I, simply, never felt the
need of it. Not that I don't have an expressive voice in my head which wants to
speak out and thwart some people, or ramble about some totally irrelevant,
pointless topic from time to time; but I never really got the urge to really
write up something and put it out there. I rarely post Facebook updates about
something that is going through my mind or something that I want to talk about.
Many things that I do want to talk about, say to a larger audience, even if
that is something which most people don't talk about, they are already neat and
snappy memes shared hundreds of times on Facebook, so I just reshare them. I
sometimes tweet about things which are small, mostly news, on twitter; and
maybe some interesting quote some time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then why did I choose to start my own web log or blog? The story behind it is
completely orthogonal to a regular person's motivation to start a blog, typical me.
Recently, I came across this static site generator called
&lt;a href="http://getpelican.com"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; which is a very popular and well known static
generators in the &lt;em&gt;hacker&lt;/em&gt; world and the world of &lt;a href="https://python.org"&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;.
I have heard of this before and looked into before, but I never paid much
attention to it. But I don't remember how, I just stumbled across this static
site generator few days back. And since then I have been toy-ing with the idea
to use Pelican, write some totally random crap, and put up some content on any
of the dirt cheap cloud hosting providers or even publish to Github pages for
free! So that's the story behind starting my blog: to try out &lt;strong&gt;Pelican&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you are a programmer, developer or software engineer, and do not have a
blog yet, and have been etching to start your own blog - I highly recommend
&lt;a href="http://getpelican.com"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Said all of the above and have started a blog, I plan to continue this blog.  I
don't know yet what I'll be posting or writing here, I think that will become
more clear with time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's see where this goes from here!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="random"></category><category term="blogging"></category><category term="history"></category></entry><entry><title>Hello World</title><link href="/hello-world.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-02-08T21:10:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-02-08T21:10:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Anon Ray</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-02-08:/hello-world.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello world&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Hello World!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The customary Hello World from a programmer. Even on his blog.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="random"></category></entry></feed>